<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>OnSaddle</title>
  
  <subtitle>Nine-Dragon Well</subtitle>
  <link href="/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  
  <link href="https://onsaddle.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2022-11-19T18:11:41.202Z</updated>
  <id>https://onsaddle.github.io/</id>
  
  <author>
    <name>Wolf</name>
    
  </author>
  
  <generator uri="https://hexo.io/">Hexo</generator>
  
  <entry>
    <title>玩弹</title>
    <link href="https://onsaddle.github.io/2022/11/19/20221119-slingshot/"/>
    <id>https://onsaddle.github.io/2022/11/19/20221119-slingshot/</id>
    <published>2022-11-19T08:06:24.000Z</published>
    <updated>2022-11-19T18:11:41.202Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>上半年时，机缘巧合承揽了一个以现代白话文翻译南北朝古史的活儿。</p><p>这两年疫情扰攘，自由译者要度过寒冬不容易，接下这个酬劳不高而难度却不低的事来做，一来是觉得史书文字量大，可以有一阶段的稳定收入，二来是它很难得地和这些年我从《读史方舆纪要》、《水经注》延伸而来的对历史地理的兴趣相关。</p><p>一千六百多年前的历史，除了要理清史事进程还有无数的地名、官职、典故需要弄懂，间或更是夹有字词艰深句法瑰异的六朝骈文，翻译起来为了信达雅，遣词造句必须几经推敲。久而久之几乎要精神分裂出一个旁观的看客ego，看着苦苦查资料的自己作茧自缚而幸灾乐祸。</p><p>长期伏案工作，当然需要有放松身心的户外活动来平衡。疫情处处设卡，骑行是没希望了。最极简的跑步从下半年起又捡起来了，以全马为目标来跟着计划训练，跑量逐月积累。半程马拉松的PB跑出了1：50：05，似乎可以和十年前持平了。但是3次半马过后，逐渐感到长距离的训练压力甚大，还要兼顾营养和运动后的恢复，花的精力着实不少，很难有余力攻关古史。</p><p>机缘巧合，九月接触弹弓，现在逐渐取代跑步成为新的户外爱好。</p><p>这个东西很有意思。它很古，归在古代“君子六艺”的射艺里面。古代的弹弓，史书上称之为弹，形制与射箭的弓很像，惟弓弦有差异而已。据我考证，它是华夏/汉民族的发明，匈奴鲜卑等游牧民族至迟到魏晋时都无此习俗。</p><p>《魏书》上记载，北魏的立国始祖拓跋力微与三国的曹魏和亲，并把太子沙漠汗送到洛阳作人质，在洛阳一住就是十多年。拓跋力微年老之后，沙漠汗请求北归，这时已经是西晋了，晋武帝就备下锦绣丝绢等厚礼送他回去。</p><p>拓跋力微派鲜卑贵族远远地迎接太子，大摆酒宴，喝到兴头上，天空中传来鸿雁声声，沙漠汗就对众人说：“我给列位露一手。” 说着拉开弓就是一弹丸，飞雁应弦而落。鲜卑人射箭，却没有玩弹的习俗。在场的鲜卑各部大人见太子不用箭矢就射下飞鸟，全都大吃一惊。</p><p>当时，“狡猾狡猾地” 晋武帝见沙漠汗英武过人，怕他北归之后难以羁縻，早已暗中送了大量金帛给这些大人，离间他们和太子之间的关系。他们果然回去后向拓跋力微汇报说，太子才艺非常，引空弓而落飞鸟，是得了晋人的奇技淫巧，乃乱国害民之兆。</p><p>拓跋力微这时已经有点老糊涂，加上太子长期驻外，更宠爱留在身边的儿子，竟信了谗言同意把沙漠汗处死，事后追悔莫及，不久也去世了。</p><p><code>始祖闻帝归，大悦，使诸部大人诣阴馆迎之。酒酣，帝仰视飞鸟，谓诸大人曰：“我为汝曹取之。”援弹飞丸，应弦而落。时国俗无弹，众咸大惊，乃相谓曰：“太子风彩被服，同于南夏，兼奇术绝世，若继国统，变易旧俗，吾等必不得志，不若在国诸子，习本淳朴。”咸以为然。且离间素行，乃谋危害，并先驰还。始祖问曰：“我子既历他国，进德何如？”皆对曰：“太子才艺非常，引空弓而落飞鸟，是似得晋人异法怪术，乱国害民之兆，惟愿察之。”自帝在晋之后，诸子爱宠日进，始祖年逾期颐，颇有所惑，闻诸大人之语，意乃有疑。因曰：“不可容者，便当除之。”于是诸大人乃驰诣塞南，矫害帝。既而，始祖甚悔之。</code></p><p>沙漠汗喜提“因玩弹弓而失去王位乃至生命之第一人”。</p><p>古代弹弓的原理和弓箭一样，主要是利用弓身而不是弓弦的形变势能来射击。19世纪橡胶工业诞生之后，才逐渐出现了利用弓弦的形变势能来射击的现代弹弓，也就是小时候自己做过的Y形的那种。</p><p>长途骑行时有时会被路过村庄的恶狗追赶。有过几次这种惊险经历以后，我向其他长途骑友取经，曾经买了把弹弓放在包里算是防身，后来却一次也没用上，大概是恶狗也觉我面善了吧。</p><p>19年骑行去随州，返程坐火车进站时被工作人员拦下，原来是不锈钢弹弓被X光机检出，属于不能携带上列车的禁品。只好留给他们玩了。</p><p>生而为人已倍感禁锢，自由飞翔的鸟雀，怀而慕之，怎忍害其性命？如今的弹弓对我而言，是纯粹的健身运动用品。在林中端正姿态，调整气息，引而不发，凝目度测，都是过程之美。松手释放，命中标靶的一声脆响传来，心头忽而感到一阵轻快，那一刻的意气自如最是难忘。发而不中，反求诸己。即便连续失准也不急躁，因为和射弹过程的一系列修正谐调自身相比，最后弹丸有没有击中悬垂的空瓶，已经是不需要过于执着的了。</p><p>拉弓瞄准时碰上阵风吹来，弓弦的嗡嗡之声让人心神旷远。几千年的大小战事，多少铜铁矢簇在空中飞行，坠入泥土或是穿透甲胄，又有多少血肉之躯感受到金属的彻骨锋锐，从此了无声息跌入尘埃。</p><p>生命的本质是能量。拉动弹弓，我把我的一小部分生命转移到了弹丸上。它飞走了，穿越凛冽远去。我看见一小部分的我获得了自由，一意孤行地完成冥冥中的轨迹。粉碎也好，完整也罢，余音终于融入寂静，融入万籁。</p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        &lt;p&gt;上半年时，机缘巧合承揽了一个以现代白话文翻译南北朝古史的活儿。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;这两年疫情扰攘，自由译者要度过寒冬不容易，接下这个酬劳不高而难度却不低的事来做，一来是觉得史书文字量大，可以有一阶段的稳定收入，二来是它很难得地和这些年我从《读史方舆纪要》、《水经注》延伸而来的对
      
    
    </summary>
    
    
      <category term="Skiff" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/categories/Skiff/"/>
    
    
      <category term="slingshot" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/tags/slingshot/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>霈琳 &amp; 輝 Having a Baby</title>
    <link href="https://onsaddle.github.io/2022/06/07/Having-a-Baby/"/>
    <id>https://onsaddle.github.io/2022/06/07/Having-a-Baby/</id>
    <published>2022-06-07T08:06:24.000Z</published>
    <updated>2022-06-07T13:33:39.066Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last month my former colleague 霈琳 (sometimes I call her 女神經小姐) gave birth to a cute baby girl. </p><p>She and her husband 輝 live in Zhanjiang in Guangdong. They are my  friends and I had encouraged them to tie the knot for quite some time.  But I knew they had some ups and downs even before I left Guangdong for  Wuhan. Finally last winter they made the call. That gave me great  relief, because they REALLY are a perfect match and to see people like  them miss each other out would definetely break my heart. </p><p> I sent a little gift to the new parents and 輝, who is a talented  barista, sent me two packs of freshly roasted coffee beans. He knew I’m a coffee drinker. </p><p>I haven’t visited his cafe Old House yet, which he co-founded with  friends after his previous cafe business, a cafe joint on a mini-van  called STAY Coffee Bus, ceased to operate following some rifts between  him and the investor.  </p><p> I was a fan of STAY. In 2017 when I visited them I spent half a day with 輝 working in this little cafe bus.</p><p>It was something that you can call a “dream”. I know not too many men  live to work on their dreams, on every details and all the challenges  that come along. It deserved better. </p><p> Baby it’s good to see a fresh new life brought into this world. The world is flawed. We are flawed. A new life is flawless. </p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        &lt;p&gt;Last month my former colleague 霈琳 (sometimes I call her 女神經小姐) gave birth to a cute baby girl. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She and her husband 輝 live in Zhan
      
    
    </summary>
    
    
      <category term="Yangtze" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/categories/Yangtze/"/>
    
    
      <category term="friends" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/tags/friends/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Ballads of the North 樂府英譯——北朝民歌一束</title>
    <link href="https://onsaddle.github.io/2022/01/13/northern-songs/"/>
    <id>https://onsaddle.github.io/2022/01/13/northern-songs/</id>
    <published>2022-01-13T08:06:24.000Z</published>
    <updated>2022-01-19T16:53:02.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Some ancient nomadic peoples in northern Asia, like Xiongnu 匈奴, Xianbei 鮮卑 and Rouran 柔然, didn’t develop a writing system for their languages. Their heterogeneous confederations usually consisted of a variety of tribal groups, whose cultures and customs spread across the steppe and then, when their states and dynasties were no more, simply merged into the latecomers’.</p><p>Sometimes I wonder if this would be a cleaner, happier way of existence - no need to learn how to write. For your relatively short life expectancy, just speak what you think, and let the next wind carry it away. No diary, no blog. No journalism, no tomes of classics and no exam papers for the kids. No glory to pass down. No lies to repeat. When night falls and bonfire rises, you sing. </p><p>When you die, your songs might be sung by neighbours and children, or not. Clans and generations, great loves and legendary warriors, all disappear after one or two blizzards in the history. Really clean.</p><p>This, understandably, posed a challenge to the preserving of history record and literature. A strange hobby of some compulsive obsessionists, no doubt.</p><p>But there was always the Han Chinese. Boy did we love writing. We worshipped it, creating different forms of scrips, making many an arts and inventions for it. To be able to write was like to be able to interpret ancestors and saints, gods and emperors. Thanks to the records of the Han Chinese, some cultural traces of the disappeared nomads were preserved.</p><p>Such as the folk songs of the Northern Dynasties (386 - 581 CE) 北朝民歌. They are mostly ballads of Xianbei people, singing about wars, steeds, young lovers and scenery of the north, and were dutifully collected by the music department (called Yuefu 樂府) of the Southern Dynasties established by the Han. Compared to the folk songs in the south, which were often sung by female singers using many puns and metaphors, these northern songs are distinctively less feminine, much bolder and more straightforward. (<em>Poem of Mulan</em> <em>木蘭詩</em>  is one celebrated example.)</p><p>The nameless Yuefu translators did their job well and skilfully. Centuries later, we can still recite these beautiful lyrics, even chant them in rhythm, enjoying the vivid images they inspire. But please bear in mind - they are mostly results of Han translators’ rendition. The original ballads were sung in the tongue of the nomads, who loved singing in their lifetime so much that, they didn’t bother to entrust their songs to any form of writing. </p><p>I understand and respect that. Life is short. Sing.</p><p><img src="https://s2.loli.net/2022/01/14/xRmiWVOqZk5SbtI.jpg" alt="R-C.49ed8a17dc8a6e787ae93839aed84b13.jpg"></p><hr><p>Here goes my rendition of a handful of these northern songs:</p><br><p><strong>Songs of Picking Willow Branches</strong>  </p><blockquote><p>(Translator’s note: according to an old Chinese tradition, willow branches, a token of sadness and lingering thoughts, were often presented as a farewell gift between loved ones or friends)</p></blockquote><br><p>~ Time to bid goodbye. I mounted my horse</p><p>~ Instead of a whip, I reached for a branch of willow</p><p>~ On top of the saddle I crossed my legs. Sound of long flute gently flew</p><p>~ How many roads could a traveller ride down, before he was crushed by his sorrow</p><br><p> (sung by rider’s wife)</p><p>~ I saw my man off. Sorrow weighed down my heart</p><p>~ To be close to him I wished to be his whip</p><p>~ Far or near he rides, I would curl around his arm</p><p>~ When he crosses his legs, I would curl around his knees</p><br><p>~ Pasturing my horse in the Twin Spring Marsh</p><p>~ I was a fool to forget to tie its feet</p><p>~ Shouldering the saddle I chased my pony</p><p>~ When would you stop and be a fine steed </p><br><p>~ I rode till I laid my eyes on River Mengjin</p><p>~ Poplars and willows lined its banks, whirling and dancing  </p><p>~ In a southern tongue I heard someone singing </p><p>~ This Xianbei herdsman could not fathom its meaning</p><br><p>~ A valiant man calls for a swift horse</p><p>~ A swift horse calls for a valiant master</p><p>~ Hero or coward? Not for a game of words to decide</p><p>~ A fierce horseback duel, then, the answer will arise</p><br><br><blockquote><p><strong>折楊柳歌辭</strong></p><br><p>其一</p><p>上馬不捉鞭，</p><p>反折楊柳枝。 </p><p>蹀座吹長笛， </p><p>愁殺行客兒。 </p><br><p>其二 </p><p>腹中愁不樂， </p><p>願做郎馬鞭。 </p><p>出入擐郎臂， </p><p>蹀座郎膝邊。 </p><br><p>其三</p><p>放馬兩泉澤， </p><p>忘不著連羈。 </p><p>擔鞍逐馬走， </p><p>何見得馬騎。 </p><br><p>其四</p><p>遙看孟津河， </p><p>楊柳鬱婆娑。 </p><p>我是虜家兒， </p><p>不解漢兒歌。 </p><br><p>其五</p><p>健兒須快馬， </p><p>快馬須健兒。 </p><p>蹕跋黃塵下， </p><p>然後決雌雄。</p></blockquote>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        &lt;p&gt;Some ancient nomadic peoples in northern Asia, like Xiongnu 匈奴, Xianbei 鮮卑 and Rouran 柔然, didn’t develop a writing system for their langu
      
    
    </summary>
    
    
      <category term="Skiff" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/categories/Skiff/"/>
    
    
      <category term="poem" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/tags/poem/"/>
    
      <category term="translation" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/tags/translation/"/>
    
      <category term="Yuefu" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/tags/Yuefu/"/>
    
      <category term="nomads" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/tags/nomads/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Translation of Beidao&#39;s poem Last Words 北島《宣告》英譯</title>
    <link href="https://onsaddle.github.io/2021/06/03/Last-Words/"/>
    <id>https://onsaddle.github.io/2021/06/03/Last-Words/</id>
    <published>2021-06-03T08:06:24.000Z</published>
    <updated>2021-06-03T23:31:08.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last Words</p><p>　dedicated to a martyr, Yu Luoke </p><p>by Beidao (1949 - )</p><br>The final moment has arrived, I think<p>I left no will </p><p>　only a pen, to my mother</p><p>I am not a Hero</p><p>In an era that sustains no Hero</p><p>I just wanted to be a Man</p><p>The silent horizon  </p><p>　separates the dead from the living</p><p>I had to choose the sky</p><p>Never kneel on the earth </p><p>　to let the executioners look tall  </p><p>　　so they can stem the wind of freedom</p><p>Out of the stars - my bullet holes</p><p>A red dawn will spew</p><br>譯者注： 一九七零年三月，《出身論》作者遇羅克於北京工體萬人公判大會上獲判死刑。十年後，紛擾稍止，詩人北島寫下短詩《宣告》，擬想遇羅克赴死心境。今值慘案卅贰周年，譯以志悼。<p>原詩：</p><blockquote><p>宣 告<br>——给遇罗克烈士<br>北岛</p><br><p>也许最后的时刻到了<br>我没有留下遗嘱<br>只留下笔，给我的母亲<br>我并不是英雄<br>在没有英雄的年代里，<br>我只想做一个人。<br>宁静的地平线<br>分开了生者和死者的行列<br>我只能选择天空<br>决不跪在地上<br>以显出刽子手们的高大<br>好阻挡自由的风<br>从星星的弹孔里<br>将流出血红的黎明</p></blockquote>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        &lt;p&gt;Last Words&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;　dedicated to a martyr, Yu Luoke &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;by Beidao (1949 - )&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
The final moment has arrived, I think

&lt;p&gt;I left 
      
    
    </summary>
    
    
      <category term="Skiff" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/categories/Skiff/"/>
    
    
      <category term="poem" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/tags/poem/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Hostility from World and Friendship from Chinese Bulbul 世界的敵意與鳥兒的友情</title>
    <link href="https://onsaddle.github.io/2020/06/27/Hostility-from-World/"/>
    <id>https://onsaddle.github.io/2020/06/27/Hostility-from-World/</id>
    <published>2020-06-27T08:06:24.000Z</published>
    <updated>2022-01-13T07:51:12.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>疫病滿人間</p><p>也許佛陀需要一個沒有醫保的小翻譯覺悟</p><p>或許他擔心自由讓我忘記世事險惡（并沒有）</p><br><p>甲潑尼龍，奧美拉挫，厄貝沙坦，雙嘧達默</p><p>名字凶險的28顆白粒子</p><p>每天服用，欲仙欲死的苦</p><p>期待著醫生老爺描述的不良反應：</p><p>“…焦慮、興奮、欣快或抑鬱、失眠、性格改變、精神失常、癲癇發作…”</p><br><p>窗臺上，用葵花子和麥粒</p><p>我跟小區一群白頭鵯建立了友誼</p><p>承蒙慨允，他們容我架好相機再退回屋内</p><p>攝下就餐或避雨的肖像</p><p>偶爾晚起  沒有佈上清晨的食糧</p><p>他們依然在紗窗前如約獻歌</p><br><p>烏鶇的歌喉更殷勤些</p><p>但他們已經生了今年的幼鳥</p><p>忙著帶娃</p><p>情歌不太能聽見了</p><br><p><img src="https://i.loli.net/2020/06/27/DVvoxcAWPGuyLUM.jpg" alt="DSCN6614.JPG"></p><p><img src="https://i.loli.net/2020/06/27/fsdZKznJvq5VSyr.jpg" alt="DSCN66131.jpg"></p><p><img src="https://i.loli.net/2020/06/27/JjYfWX6Rda5Nkig.jpg" alt="DSCN6636.JPG"></p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        &lt;p&gt;疫病滿人間&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;也許佛陀需要一個沒有醫保的小翻譯覺悟&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;或許他擔心自由讓我忘記世事險惡（并沒有）&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;

&lt;p&gt;甲潑尼龍，奧美拉挫，厄貝沙坦，雙嘧達默&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;名字凶險的28顆白粒子&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;每天服用，欲仙欲死的苦&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p
      
    
    </summary>
    
    
      <category term="Skiff" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/categories/Skiff/"/>
    
    
      <category term="birding" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/tags/birding/"/>
    
      <category term="illness" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/tags/illness/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Birding from Cage 籠中觀鳥</title>
    <link href="https://onsaddle.github.io/2020/04/13/Birding-from-Cage/"/>
    <id>https://onsaddle.github.io/2020/04/13/Birding-from-Cage/</id>
    <published>2020-04-13T08:06:24.000Z</published>
    <updated>2020-04-13T18:17:28.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://i.loli.net/2020/04/14/QlYBkhjKAOCco9b.jpg" alt="DSCN6162.jpg"><em>山斑鳩 Streptopelia orientalis，Oriental Turtle Dove</em></p><p><img src="https://i.loli.net/2020/04/14/lWqJs3c5H6ajxUQ.jpg" alt="DSCN6180.jpg"><em>烏鶇 Turdus merula，Eurasian Black Bird. Extremely skilled singers. Only male adults are black.</em></p><p><img src="https://i.loli.net/2020/04/14/5etSZMo4X7ynmUK.jpg" alt="DSCN61972.jpg"><em>白頭鵯 Pycnonotus sinensis，Chinese Bulbul</em> </p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.loli.net/2020/04/14/QlYBkhjKAOCco9b.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;DSCN6162.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;山斑鳩 Streptopelia orientalis，Oriental Turtle Dove&lt;/em&gt;
      
    
    </summary>
    
    
      <category term="Yangtze" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/categories/Yangtze/"/>
    
    
      <category term="birding" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/tags/birding/"/>
    
      <category term="COVID-19" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/tags/COVID-19/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Du Fu &quot;A Traveller&#39;s Reveries at Night&quot;  杜甫《旅夜書懷》英譯</title>
    <link href="https://onsaddle.github.io/2020/04/11/Du-Fu-Travellers-Reveries/"/>
    <id>https://onsaddle.github.io/2020/04/11/Du-Fu-Travellers-Reveries/</id>
    <published>2020-04-11T08:06:24.000Z</published>
    <updated>2020-04-14T18:39:54.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>杜甫的《旅夜書懷》應寫於他離開成都、流寓蜀地楚地間的晚年。</p><p>少陵一生的抱負是輔佐明君，效仿堯舜來施行仁政，然科舉屢試不第，求仕多年，僅在長安、華州等地短期任過幾個小官，很快就因遭貶斥或不習慣官場污濁而去職。他人生的青壯年時代，正值盛唐之末，把持朝政的李林甫、楊國忠之輩對文人學士采取打壓政策，朝廷吏治趨向腐敗，同時邊鎮坐大，割據之勢積重難返。隨後的安史之亂，兵燹飢饉與疫病橫行，人口大量死亡。</p><p>在這樣的亂世下，除了不斷寫下針砭現實的詩文，杜甫顛沛流離的生活是很不如意的，常常全家陷於窮愁境地，要靠朋友接濟才免於凍餓。幼子因飢餓而逝于奉先，給他留下巨大的悲痛。</p><p>這首詩的前半部分寫景，貌似大氣磅礴，卻蘊涵一種空闊、寂靜的情緒，絕不似曹孟德《步出夏門行》的雄渾豪邁。在一片星月壯闊的畫面下，映襯出後半部分悲愴感懷的寥落。</p><p>喜讀一切關於長江的詩，不僅是因爲我在長江邊長大，更因爲在不同作者的眼中，這條河流呈現著不同的形態。人的生命，面對時間長河會顯得十分短暫微茫，但文字記錄下的瞬間感悟，有時卻能穿越時空，打動另一個靈魂。</p><br><p><strong>A Traveller’s Reveries at Night</strong></p><p>Du Fu (712 - 770)</p><br><p>Slender grass. Gentle breeze. Void river banks.</p><p>​    In the silence of night swings the lofty mast of my lone skiff.</p><p>Low hanging stars. Far stretching fields.</p><p>​    Upon the running Yangtze shivers the moon’s reflection.</p><p>How odd, that reputation can come out of one’s prose.</p><p>​    Sick leave and retirement, is surely the appropriate ending for an official career.</p><p>Drifting on and on. I wonder what a life like this resembles.</p><p>​    Ah, yes, a sand gull ever gliding between heaven and earth.</p><blockquote><p><strong>旅夜書懷</strong></p><p>杜甫</p><p>細草微風岸，危艢獨夜舟</p><p>星垂平野闊，月湧大江流</p><p>名豈文章著，官應老病休</p><p>飄飄何所似，天地一沙鷗               </p></blockquote><br><p><img src="https://i.loli.net/2020/04/12/IS7i9WFqfDvKwBu.jpg" alt="IMG_6245.JPG"><em>2014年12月，蘇州月夜</em></p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        &lt;p&gt;杜甫的《旅夜書懷》應寫於他離開成都、流寓蜀地楚地間的晚年。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;少陵一生的抱負是輔佐明君，效仿堯舜來施行仁政，然科舉屢試不第，求仕多年，僅在長安、華州等地短期任過幾個小官，很快就因遭貶斥或不習慣官場污濁而去職。他人生的青壯年時代，正值盛唐之末，把持朝政的李林甫、楊
      
    
    </summary>
    
    
      <category term="Skiff" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/categories/Skiff/"/>
    
    
      <category term="poem" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/tags/poem/"/>
    
      <category term="translation" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/tags/translation/"/>
    
      <category term="Du Fu" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/tags/Du-Fu/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Tide Changes 潮水涨落不定</title>
    <link href="https://onsaddle.github.io/2020/03/19/Tide-Changes/"/>
    <id>https://onsaddle.github.io/2020/03/19/Tide-Changes/</id>
    <published>2020-03-18T17:33:08.000Z</published>
    <updated>2020-03-19T18:37:26.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://i.loli.net/2020/03/19/imae8lCXPJy5Btr.jpg" alt="DSC_1845.JPG"><em>中间包饺子的男青年是和平队志愿者，遗憾我忘了他的名字</em></p><p>2017除夕在海口巴纳纳青旅认识了一个年轻的和平队志愿者，他正穿着和平队的褐色Tee，个子不高，友善但有点腼腆，一个人打着青旅的台球。和他玩了一局美式九球，边打边聊。</p><p>他来自南达科他州（见我我反应有点迟疑他给我看了拉什莫尔山的照片，果然有效），硕士第二年参加了和平队，在重庆江津教英语。他也觉得何伟的书不错，还说他的书让和平队在国内的知名度提升了不少。我说很多中国人可不怎么喜欢你们新上任的总统（川普）啊，他笑道，我们也都不喜欢他。</p><p>3年过去了。刚刚驱逐了一批纸媒驻华记者，和平队也撤了，<a href="https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2020/03/16/the-peace-corps-breaks-ties-with-china" target="_blank" rel="noopener">何伟的《纽约客》专栏</a>早已经在墙内无法访问。看了友邻的中译版。</p><p>涪陵的白鹤梁并没有变，只有江水涨起落下，视线看不到了而已。封锁中的城市和国度，顺行还是逆行，包容还是驱赶，观察的人就和涪陵的白鹤梁一样，也是不会变的。</p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.loli.net/2020/03/19/imae8lCXPJy5Btr.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;DSC_1845.JPG&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;中间包饺子的男青年是和平队志愿者，遗憾我忘了他的名字&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2017除夕在海口巴纳纳青旅
      
    
    </summary>
    
    
      <category term="Skiff" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/categories/Skiff/"/>
    
    
      <category term="Peace Corps" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/tags/Peace-Corps/"/>
    
      <category term="Peter Hessler" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/tags/Peter-Hessler/"/>
    
      <category term="open up" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/tags/open-up/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Oriole, An Elegy 《詩經·黃鳥》英譯</title>
    <link href="https://onsaddle.github.io/2019/12/26/Oriole-poem/"/>
    <id>https://onsaddle.github.io/2019/12/26/Oriole-poem/</id>
    <published>2019-12-26T08:06:24.000Z</published>
    <updated>2020-03-03T13:33:38.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last night I stayed up all night browsing the <a href="http://www.simplycycling.org" target="_blank" rel="noopener">blog</a> of late American adventure cyclists, Jay and Lauren. The couple was murdered last August in the Pamir mountains on their cross-continent trip. </p><br><p>Today when turning the pages of <em>Classic of Poetry 詩經</em>, this short poem 《黃鳥》 came to my eyes. </p><br><p>It was an elegy for the three brothers (子車奄息，子車仲行，子車鍼虎) of Ziju 子車 clan in Qin state 秦國, who were all celebrated warriors. When their lord - Duke Mu 秦穆公 - died in 621 BC, the three brothers were slain as human sacrifices so they could guard the dead duke in his afterlife. </p><br><p>In their life time the men were popular among the martial people of Qin, who admired their strength and courage greatly. Songs were written in memory of them and this particular one was later colleced into the book. </p><br><p>Four hundred years after their death, Emperor Qin Shihuang 秦始皇, Duke Mu’s descendant, guarded his own mausoleum with a terracotta army instead of real warriors.</p><br><p>I dedicate this translation to the two short yet enriched lives - Jay Austin and Lauren Geoghegan. </p><br><p>R.I.P.</p><br><p><img src="https://i.loli.net/2019/12/26/7q4pCtTGuL6Ok8s.jpg" alt="Jay-and-Lauren2resized-1000x563.jpg"></p><p><u><em>courtesy of <a href="http://www.simplycycling.org" target="_blank" rel="noopener">simplycycling.org</a></em></u></p><br><blockquote><p><strong>黃鳥</strong></p><br><p><em>詩經 | 國風 | 秦風</em> </p><br><p>交交黃鳥，<br>止於棘。<br>誰從穆公？<br>子車奄息。<br>維此奄息，<br>百夫之特。<br>臨其穴，<br>惴惴其慄。<br>彼蒼者天，<br>殲我良人！<br>如可贖兮，<br>人百其身！</p><br><p>交交黃鳥，<br>止於桑。<br>誰從穆公？<br>子車仲行。<br>維此仲行，<br>百夫之防。<br>臨其穴，<br>惴惴其慄。<br>彼蒼者天，<br>殲我良人！<br>如可贖兮，<br>人百其身！</p><br><p>交交黃鳥，<br>止於楚。<br>誰從穆公？<br>子車鍼虎。<br>維此鍼虎，<br>百夫之禦。<br>臨其穴，<br>惴惴其慄。<br>彼蒼者天，<br>殲我良人！<br>如可贖兮，<br>人百其身！</p></blockquote><p><strong>Oriole</strong></p><br><p><em>Airs of Qin | Airs of States | Classic of Poetry</em></p><br><p>Cooing and cooing, the oriole sang.<br>Yet his song subsided on the thorn branch.<br>Who followed Duke Mu to the underground?<br>It was Yanxi of the Ziju clan;<br>The same Yanxi who<br>   was a match of a hundred men.<br>Before his tomb here I stand.<br>Torn is my heart, agitated is my mind.<br>You high there, the void Heaven,<br>You took away our finest sons!<br>Could his life be ransomed, here<br>   are one hundred of us, to trade for this one！  </p><br><p>Cooing and cooing, the oriole sang.<br>Yet his song stopped on the mulberry branch.<br>Who followed Duke Mu to the underground?<br>It was Zhongxing of the Ziju clan;<br>The same Zhongxing who<br>   could hold off a hundred men.<br>Before his tomb here I stand.<br>Torn is my heart, agitated is my mind.<br>You high there, the void Heaven,<br>You took away our finest sons!<br>Could his life be ransomed, here<br>   are one hundred of us, to trade for this one！  </p><br><p>Cooing and cooing, the oriole sang.<br>Yet his song snapped on the bramble branch.<br>Who followed Duke Mu to the underground?<br>It was Zhenhu of the Ziju clan;<br>The one and the same Zhenhu<br>   as the bravest centurion.<br>Before his tomb here I stand.<br>Torn is my heart, agitated is my mind.<br>You high there, the void Heaven,<br>You took away our finest sons!<br>Could his life be ransomed, here<br>   are one hundred of us, to trade for this one！</p><br><br><p>2019年12月26日下午譯畢</p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        &lt;p&gt;Last night I stayed up all night browsing the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.simplycycling.org&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt; of late Amer
      
    
    </summary>
    
    
      <category term="Skiff" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/categories/Skiff/"/>
    
    
      <category term="poem" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/tags/poem/"/>
    
      <category term="translation" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/tags/translation/"/>
    
      <category term="Classic of Poetry" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/tags/Classic-of-Poetry/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Fermenting November 冬月，釀酒焙麥</title>
    <link href="https://onsaddle.github.io/2019/12/05/Nov-bake/"/>
    <id>https://onsaddle.github.io/2019/12/05/Nov-bake/</id>
    <published>2019-12-05T08:06:24.000Z</published>
    <updated>2020-03-03T13:44:22.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Cold November days, as grey as my old depression. </p><p>Made a jar of rice wine 米酒 after solar term of Winter Start 立冬, which I mistook for another, more celebrated one, the Winter Solstice 冬至, following an old rural tradition of my hometown.</p><p>Made 2 lbs of spicy beef jerky and sent it along with the rice wine to my sis as a gift. </p><p>Started a long-term project of sampling survey of Hot Dry Noodle 熱幹面 joints across Wuhan.</p><p><img src="https://i.loli.net/2019/12/23/jO3qmxaU98hQbtG.jpg" alt="20191223233514.jpg"><u>about 14 degree of alcohol</u></p><p><img src="https://i.loli.net/2019/12/05/hneWMuBCf9GpOSa.jpg" alt="20191115021412.jpg"><u>Naan</u></p><p><img src="https://i.loli.net/2019/12/05/mukoM78qD5rKIxZ.jpg" alt="DSCN5768.JPG"><u>Рижский хлеб</u></p><p><img src="https://i.loli.net/2019/12/05/ONPUzjSRZfXQY39.jpg" alt="DSCN5755.JPG"></p><p><img src="https://i.loli.net/2019/12/05/QvaTM57weonOYWb.jpg" alt="DSCN5752.JPG"><u>Rye bread with fermented bean curd 腐乳 rocks</u></p><p><img src="https://i.loli.net/2019/12/05/QiwltIgXuSWMAEH.jpg" alt="20191205233353.jpg"><u>Pumpkin bread</u></p><p><img src="https://i.loli.net/2019/12/05/uwAHNY2dZaW8Sn7.jpg" alt="20191205233300.jpg"></p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        &lt;p&gt;Cold November days, as grey as my old depression. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Made a jar of rice wine 米酒 after solar term of Winter Start 立冬, which I mistook
      
    
    </summary>
    
    
      <category term="WhatsCooking" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/categories/WhatsCooking/"/>
    
    
      <category term="bread" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/tags/bread/"/>
    
      <category term="baking" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/tags/baking/"/>
    
      <category term="food" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/tags/food/"/>
    
      <category term="wine" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/tags/wine/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Conscripted at Fifteen 十五從軍徵</title>
    <link href="https://onsaddle.github.io/2019/11/25/Conscripted-at-fifteen/"/>
    <id>https://onsaddle.github.io/2019/11/25/Conscripted-at-fifteen/</id>
    <published>2019-11-25T08:06:24.000Z</published>
    <updated>2022-01-13T08:09:38.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>十五從軍徵<br>八十始得歸<br>道逢鄉里人<br>家中有阿誰<br>遙看是君家<br>松柏塚累累<br>兔從狗竇入<br>雉從樑上飛<br>中庭生旅谷<br>井上生旅葵<br>舂谷持作飯<br>採葵持作羹<br>羹飯一時熟<br>不知遗阿誰<br>出門東向看<br>淚落沾我衣</p></blockquote><p>This is a well-known Yuefu 樂府 ballad, written probably during the violent final years of Eastern Han dynasty and Three Kingdoms era in the 3rd century, depicting an old man’s visit to the ruins of his old family house after a lifelong forced service in the army. </p><p>It is a heart-breaking image. Barren, empty fields in the winter. Ruins of old houses after many wars. Tombs, old and new, crowded. Homeless old man. </p><br><hr><br><p>Conscripted at fifteen,<br>  Only discharged at eighty.<br><br></p><p>Met a traveler from home village,<br>  “Who’s still living in my family?”<br><br></p><p>“Over there was your cottage,” said he,<br>  “Now home to pines, cypresses and a cemetery.”<br><br></p><p>Hares scuttled in through the dog hole,<br>  Pheasants fluttered above the old beam.<br><br></p><p>In the courtyard ripened wild grain,<br>  On top of the well flourished a mallow bush.<br><br></p><p>Pestled the grain to make pot of rice,<br>  Plucked mallow leaves to make a pottage.<br><br></p><p>Pottage and rice were both cooked and ready,<br>  Yet with who I’d share them in this yard all empty?<br><br></p><p>Stumbling outside I looked east,<br>  Something wetted my collar, I don’t know, my old eyes were blurry.</p><br><br><hr><br><p><img src="https://i.loli.net/2020/02/12/ewmVGSNc418WkgJ.jpg" alt="DSC_1023.JPG"> <u>dusk, Jianghan plain 江漢平原, August 2020</u></p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        &lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;十五從軍徵&lt;br&gt;八十始得歸&lt;br&gt;道逢鄉里人&lt;br&gt;家中有阿誰&lt;br&gt;遙看是君家&lt;br&gt;松柏塚累累&lt;br&gt;兔從狗竇入&lt;br&gt;雉從樑上飛&lt;br&gt;中庭生旅谷&lt;br&gt;井上生旅葵&lt;br&gt;舂谷持作飯&lt;br&gt;採葵持作羹&lt;br&gt;羹飯一時熟&lt;br&gt;不知遗阿誰&lt;b
      
    
    </summary>
    
    
      <category term="Skiff" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/categories/Skiff/"/>
    
    
      <category term="poem" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/tags/poem/"/>
    
      <category term="translation" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/tags/translation/"/>
    
      <category term="homeless" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/tags/homeless/"/>
    
      <category term="Yuefu" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/tags/Yuefu/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Pot-holding Lodger 端鍋客</title>
    <link href="https://onsaddle.github.io/2019/11/10/pot-holding-lodger/"/>
    <id>https://onsaddle.github.io/2019/11/10/pot-holding-lodger/</id>
    <published>2019-11-10T08:06:24.000Z</published>
    <updated>2020-02-12T07:19:44.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://i.loli.net/2019/11/10/yiv3ITMOpRS6zCm.jpg" alt="DSC_0049.JPG"></p><br><p>貳零壹肆年歲末，余訪姑蘇，住烏鵲橋。青旅甚小，店中一客，備電飯鍋一口，日日飯蔬同炊一鍋中，熟則不列碗碟，端鍋而食，似頗甘美。余異之，與談，客甚謙謙。乃知此君由浙來蘇拜師習古琴，師父每月止授一日，悉賴自修，已住店數月，有阮囊之羞，故儉省自奉如此。求聞一曲，客赧而不許。邀共宴飲，亦皆辭謝，惟飲余所攜武夷茶一盞。居遊七日，流連吳中亭台園圃間，終未得聞其琴曲。及將離蘇，客堅送至公車站乃別。</p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.loli.net/2019/11/10/yiv3ITMOpRS6zCm.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;DSC_0049.JPG&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;

&lt;p&gt;貳零壹肆年歲末，余訪姑蘇，住烏鵲橋。青旅甚小，店中一客，備電飯鍋一口，日日飯蔬同炊一鍋
      
    
    </summary>
    
    
      <category term="Skiff" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/categories/Skiff/"/>
    
    
      <category term="travel" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/tags/travel/"/>
    
      <category term="Suzhou" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/tags/Suzhou/"/>
    
      <category term="youth hostel" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/tags/youth-hostel/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>First Loaf in 2019 今年開爐第一包</title>
    <link href="https://onsaddle.github.io/2019/11/05/first-loaf/"/>
    <id>https://onsaddle.github.io/2019/11/05/first-loaf/</id>
    <published>2019-11-05T08:06:24.000Z</published>
    <updated>2019-11-12T19:48:20.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After a year without oven and the smell of parched flour, the baking hibernation is finally over.</p><p><img src="https://i.loli.net/2019/11/05/T6AyOhwRKkcH4CM.jpg" alt="微信图片_20191105174302.jpg"></p><p>An ideal oven should be a <strong>low-tech</strong> appliance. Mine is a robust mechanically controlled 38L Dolim, freshly arrived from Foshan. </p><p>I decide to get warmed up with a rustic, nordic style loaf. The warm, slightly sour smell of rye did wake up all the memory of the coldest days in Guangzhou that year when making bread in a tiny 15L oven saved my life.</p><p><img src="https://i.loli.net/2019/11/05/cGjE64XTYsIVfe3.jpg" alt="微信图片_20191105164509.jpg"><br>dough</p><p><img src="https://i.loli.net/2019/11/07/9XqTjgzytQGrcw8.jpg" alt="微信图片_201911071224416.jpg"><br>baking</p><p><img src="https://i.loli.net/2019/11/07/JBhGcpzUmQbTsKM.jpg" alt="微信图片_201911071224412.jpg"><br>cooling</p><p><img src="https://i.loli.net/2019/11/05/iTGy1BIoHctShjv.jpg" alt="DSCN5661.JPG"><br>magic of Maillard </p><p><img src="https://i.loli.net/2019/11/05/HxNPBm618tEhqRD.jpg" alt="DSCN5667.JPG"><br>caramelised</p><p><img src="https://i.loli.net/2019/11/07/2YeP93cnyVJKDmd.jpg" alt="微信图片_20191107122206.jpg"><br>crumb structure</p><p>I can gaze at bread or dough for hours. It’s a living thing. A dough is very much like a baby.</p><p>Baking is kind of a reminder. If you can bake, you can love.</p><p><img src="https://i.loli.net/2019/11/05/AHhYjbUZm4LPg67.jpg" alt="DSCN5675.JPG"></p><p><img src="https://i.loli.net/2019/11/05/zDBYf7SOMRQmjCw.jpg" alt="DSCN5676.JPG"></p><p><img src="https://i.loli.net/2019/11/05/HFtjZWM9nBQlV3I.jpg" alt="DSCN5602.JPG"></p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        &lt;p&gt;After a year without oven and the smell of parched flour, the baking hibernation is finally over.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.loli.net/201
      
    
    </summary>
    
    
      <category term="WhatsCooking" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/categories/WhatsCooking/"/>
    
    
      <category term="bread" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/tags/bread/"/>
    
      <category term="baking" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/tags/baking/"/>
    
      <category term="food" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/tags/food/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Rapeseed Oil Noodle, A Hubei Specialty 我们湖北的油麵</title>
    <link href="https://onsaddle.github.io/2019/11/02/noodle-youmian/"/>
    <id>https://onsaddle.github.io/2019/11/02/noodle-youmian/</id>
    <published>2019-11-02T08:06:24.000Z</published>
    <updated>2022-01-13T19:26:02.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://i.loli.net/2019/11/03/F6GhRVaiKPWeyDM.jpg" alt="DSCN5567.JPG"></p><p><img src="https://i.loli.net/2019/11/03/zbWTvmPyBSaFXRZ.jpg" alt="DSCN5575.JPG"></p><p><img src="https://i.loli.net/2019/11/03/t7hTyFlpmduksWO.jpg" alt="DSC_1363.JPG"></p><p><img src="https://i.loli.net/2019/11/03/7acrVUuMKTydWBs.jpg" alt="DSCN5588.JPG"></p><hr><p>In this Oct 1st holiday I pedalled to 團風 (county about 100 km east of Wuhan, under administration of 黃岡市) and camped near 牛車河水庫 for two days, far away from bravado military parades and futile street protests. </p><p>Gathering of large number of people always arouses my strong impulse to withdraw.</p><p>I willingly accept the title of “isolationist”, “reactionist” even, or any other label that excites a nut or mob. </p><p>Here at the foot of Dabie were only hills, villages, sky, water and night stars - simple things that calm the nerves. Nature brings the better side out of humanity.</p><p>When passing through a village called 周家灣 I witnessed the production of a local handmade noodle called 油麵 （literally, Oil Noodle, a specialty noodle in 團风、羅田、英山、麻城、黃陂、武穴）. To be exact I only saw the final stages of the process - drying and packaging. Impressive. The fine noodles on the shelves - slightly pale instead of bright white because of the rapeseed oil in it - swayed in the breeze like a delicate pearl curtain.</p><p><img src="https://i.loli.net/2019/11/02/HbILGeKo1RQk8Mv.jpg" alt="DSC_1353.JPG"></p><p><img src="https://i.loli.net/2019/11/02/l9omGv7EFP23MS1.jpg" alt="DSC_1354.JPG"></p><p>The friendly father and son told me about their work with implicit pride. Made with flour, water, salt and a little rapeseed oil, the dough is first painstakingly hand-rubbed into thick strips, and is then elongated/pulled by pairs of extra-long chopsticks for multiple times into thinner threads. Then the chopsticks are attached to the wooden shelves where the noodles are pulled by its own weight into even finer threads and are air-dried outdoors in fine days. </p><p>Extra work is needed to separate the noodle threads during the drying process. The dry noodles are then neatly packed into rolls, tied up with a red string.</p><p><img src="https://i.loli.net/2019/11/02/3XCFPMxObGsUQKa.jpg" alt="DSC_1356.JPG"></p><p>It used to be a celebration food, they told me, often presented as gifts for weddings and childbirths. Now many elderly people in this part of Hubei still enjoy the noodle at home for its unparalleled flavour and texture - the fine noodle is smooth as silk, fragrant and delicious in a chicken or pork broth (I can testify on this). No cheap machine-made noodles can compete that - why it survived.  </p><p>I bought 10 yuan of noodles from them, about 1 kilo. The price is rather low for a handmade noodle, but this is central China’s countryside. I wished them good luck sincerely. The noodle felt heavy in the pannier, but remained intact for the 100 km way back. I made a chicken broth and soaked cooked noodle into the broth - a hearty Chicken Broth Noodles 鸡汤麵! The noodle was so silky. Mum praised highly of it. </p><p>I really wished I had brought back 5 kilo more.</p><p><img src="https://i.loli.net/2019/11/02/dCLYzNIvxnPUc5u.jpg" alt="DSC_1355.JPG"></p><hr><p>GPX track from Wuhan to Niuchehe Reservoir 牛車河水庫 :</p><p><a href="https://share.weiyun.com/5Jyri8n" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://share.weiyun.com/5Jyri8n</a></p><p>Need to take a ferry to cross the Yangtze at 白滸鎮 village of 葛店 town. The lone ferry boat there would only set out when there are at least five passengers obviously to cover the cost. So prepare to spend a good couple of hours at the ferry crossing. Good opportunity to strike up conversations with the locals.</p><p><img src="https://i.loli.net/2020/02/12/jvNnq19PZlpHtwA.jpg" alt="DSCN5535.JPG"></p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.loli.net/2019/11/03/F6GhRVaiKPWeyDM.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;DSCN5567.JPG&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.loli.net/2019/11/03/zbWTvmPyB
      
    
    </summary>
    
    
      <category term="Yangtze" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/categories/Yangtze/"/>
    
    
      <category term="cycling" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/tags/cycling/"/>
    
      <category term="Dabie" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/tags/Dabie/"/>
    
      <category term="Hubei" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/tags/Hubei/"/>
    
      <category term="food" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/tags/food/"/>
    
      <category term="noodle" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/tags/noodle/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Fine Drizzle - A Translation 雨絲</title>
    <link href="https://onsaddle.github.io/2019/09/19/Drizzle-Zheng-Chouyu/"/>
    <id>https://onsaddle.github.io/2019/09/19/Drizzle-Zheng-Chouyu/</id>
    <published>2019-09-19T08:06:24.000Z</published>
    <updated>2019-10-08T05:11:52.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://i.loli.net/2019/09/20/RgXtc4isZAQTON2.jpg" alt="20060829041615fb77.gif"><br>Zheng Chouyu 鄭愁予 (1933 - )</p><hr><p>鄭愁予的《雨絲》，初識于大學時很喜歡的齊豫滾石珍藏版專輯中。還記得這是磁帶B面的第4首。“我們底戀啊，像雨絲……如今已是，摔碎的珍珠，流滿人世了……” </p><p>這首詩寫於約70年前，卻依然如此動人。</p><p>我認為詩中的“蓮葉燈”實際是指蓮花燈，一種中國傳統的用於許願祈福的蓮花形燈籠，又稱寶蓮燈。故改譯為lotus lantern。</p><br><p>Fine Drizzle<br><br></p><p>Our love, was like a fine drizzle.<br>On the path from one star to another,<br>Soundlessly our carriage passed.</p><br><p>We frolicked in the transparent forest,<br>washed our feet in the waterless creek<br> —— O that riverbed, crowded with lotus lanterns,<br>where the story of Cowherd and Magpie Bridge<br> was left behind …</p><br><p>Left behind<br>was our love, like a fine drizzle,<br>slanting, swaying, woven into a pale memory.<br>But, could a pale memory find<br> eternity among the stars?<br>A shattered pearl now it becomes,<br>scattered over this Earth …  </p><br><p><em>2019年9月19日譯，22日改定</em></p><br><blockquote><p>雨絲<br><br><br>我們底戀啊，像雨絲，<br>在星斗與星斗間的路上，<br>我們的車輿是無聲的。<br><br><br>曾嬉戲於透明的大森林，<br>曾濯足于無水的小溪，<br>——那是，擠滿著蓮葉燈的河床啊，<br>是有牽牛和鵲橋的故事<br> 遺落在那裡的……<br><br><br>遺落在那裡的——<br>我們底戀啊，像雨絲，<br>斜斜地，斜斜地，織成淡的記憶。<br>而是否淡的記憶<br> 就永留於星斗之間呢？<br>如今已是摔碎的珍珠<br>流滿人世了……</p><br>1950</blockquote><br><p>李泰祥作曲，齊豫演唱的《雨絲》</p><iframe frameborder="no" border="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" width="330" height="86" src="//music.163.com/outchain/player?type=2&id=284956&auto=1&height=66"></iframe>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.loli.net/2019/09/20/RgXtc4isZAQTON2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;20060829041615fb77.gif&quot;&gt;&lt;br&gt;Zheng Chouyu 鄭愁予 (1933 - )&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;鄭愁予的
      
    
    </summary>
    
    
      <category term="Skiff" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/categories/Skiff/"/>
    
    
      <category term="poem" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/tags/poem/"/>
    
      <category term="Zheng Chouyu" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/tags/Zheng-Chouyu/"/>
    
      <category term="translation" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/tags/translation/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Translating Gu Cheng 顧城短詩一束</title>
    <link href="https://onsaddle.github.io/2019/09/16/Gu-Cheng-5-Poems/"/>
    <id>https://onsaddle.github.io/2019/09/16/Gu-Cheng-5-Poems/</id>
    <published>2019-09-16T08:06:24.000Z</published>
    <updated>2022-06-07T12:44:24.114Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Aspen Tree</strong></p><p>The moment I lost an arm，<br>I opened wide an eye.</p><br><p><strong>A Generation</strong></p><p>Dark night has left me dark eyes<br>Yet with them I search for bright light</p><br><p><strong>Snap</strong></p><p>Sunlight<br>flashed in the sky<br>then was shut by dark clouds.</p><p>Torrential rain is washing<br>the film of my soul.</p><br><p><strong>Far and Close</strong></p><p>You<br>gazed at me<br>and gazed at clouds</p><p>You felt<br>so far away when gazing at me<br>and so close when gazing at clouds</p><br><p><strong>Narrow Alley</strong></p><p>Narrow alley<br>long and winding</p><p>There’s no door<br>There’s no window</p><p>There an old key you hold<br>with which a thick wall you knock</p><br><blockquote><p><strong>楊樹</strong></p><p>我失去了一隻臂膀，<br>就睜開了一隻眼睛。<br><br></p><p><strong>一代人</strong></p><p>黑夜給了我黑色的眼睛<br>我卻用它尋找光明<br><br></p><p><strong>攝</strong></p><p>陽光<br>在天上一閃，<br>又被烏雲掩埋。</p><p>暴雨沖洗著，<br>我靈魂的底片。<br><br></p><p><strong>遠和近</strong></p><p>你<br>一會看我<br>一會看雲</p><p>我覺得<br>你看我時很遠<br>你看雲時很近<br><br></p><p><strong>小巷</strong></p><p>小巷<br>又彎又長</p><p>沒有門<br>沒有窗</p><p>你拿把舊鑰匙<br>敲著厚厚的牆</p></blockquote><hr><br><p><img src="https://i.loli.net/2019/09/16/iSmgQ5zd2TsDvYO.jpg" alt="gu_cheng_220x500.jpg"><br>Gu Cheng 顧城 (1956-1993)</p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Aspen Tree&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The moment I lost an arm，&lt;br&gt;I opened wide an eye.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A Generation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
      
    
    </summary>
    
    
      <category term="Skiff" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/categories/Skiff/"/>
    
    
      <category term="poem" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/tags/poem/"/>
    
      <category term="translation" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/tags/translation/"/>
    
      <category term="Gu Cheng" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/tags/Gu-Cheng/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Bookstore&#39;s Plan for &#39;Suicide Authors Shelf&#39; Canceled “自殺作家”專架風波</title>
    <link href="https://onsaddle.github.io/2019/08/28/bookstore-suicide-shelf/"/>
    <id>https://onsaddle.github.io/2019/08/28/bookstore-suicide-shelf/</id>
    <published>2019-08-28T08:06:24.000Z</published>
    <updated>2019-11-02T12:37:26.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A well-respected independent bookstore in Nanjing 南京 said on Weibo that <a href="http://dy.163.com/v2/article/detail/ENJ36FS80514D0JD.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">it was planning a special shelf dedicated to those authors who took their own lives, and encouraged Weibo followers to suggest a list</a>.</p><p>This marketing move caused a small buzz across social networks severe enough for the bookstore to issue an online apology the next day, saying it had abandoned the plan which “shows a lacking of respect to the late authors and also hurts the feeling of the readers.”</p><p> <img src="https://i.loli.net/2019/09/11/3IESL1cfG9xaitK.jpg" alt="cap.JPG"></p><p>I visited the “Librairie Avant-grade” 先鋒書店 four years ago and liked it. Its decoration and layout had a touch of seriousness as close to religious faith as a bookstore can get. </p><p>They had a high quality collection of books of humanity, arts and social science. I bought Dmitry Merezhkovsky’s <em>Napoleon: A Study</em> there, which proved to be the best biography and in-depth study of the emperor I have come across. (Yes, the best Napoleon study, from a Russian writer.)</p><p>One of their special services was that they offered to put a store stamp on the back of your purchased books - a nostalgic tradition that not many bookstores care to practice nowadays.</p><p>Personally I think the abandoned plan would have been a campaign that missed the point badly: suicide itself, not the variety of authors who committed it, is a worthy category/subject. As Camus put it, “there is but one really serious philosophical problem and that is suicide.”</p><hr><p><img src="https://i.loli.net/2019/09/11/hFpKWoirfLGQI17.jpg" alt="IMG_6455.JPG"> <em>Librairie Avant-grade in 2015</em></p><hr><p>The bookstore’s intention might be to highlight the weight of “suicide” as a universal theme among great minds. But simply putting up a shelf of books - not by those who thought about it, talked about it and wrote about it but by those who committed it for various reasons - would have defeated the purpose, if ever there is one.  </p><p>My feelings are not hurt at all (how silly such claims sound). On the contrary I have an amusing visualization of such a “suicide authors shelf” scenario: <br></p><blockquote><p>午夜，當書店陷入黑暗寂靜中時，作者的靈魂紛紛從封面走下來，在書架間彼此問候傾談幾句，或是在角落裡打哈欠抽煙發呆，阿嘉莎問問隔壁道爾爵士的研究新進展，納博科夫向塞林格打聽康尼什小鎮的蝴蝶萍蹤，唯有一處書架下聚了一群人默不作聲像是在賭氣，定睛一看有腦袋纏繃帶的梵古、悶頭擦獵槍的大鬍子海明威、手捧大卵石峨冠往下滴著水的屈原大夫，還有好些穿著上世紀六十年代灰藍布制服、口袋別著鋼筆的老先生。一轉身遇見茨威格，圓眼鏡氣得直閃光：“這叫一個亂！剛才我可遇著希特勒了——誰把《我的奮鬥》塞這兒來了？”</p></blockquote>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        &lt;p&gt;A well-respected independent bookstore in Nanjing 南京 said on Weibo that &lt;a href=&quot;http://dy.163.com/v2/article/detail/ENJ36FS80514D0JD.htm
      
    
    </summary>
    
    
      <category term="Yangtze" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/categories/Yangtze/"/>
    
    
      <category term="bookstore" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/tags/bookstore/"/>
    
      <category term="suicide" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/tags/suicide/"/>
    
      <category term="Nanjing" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/tags/Nanjing/"/>
    
      <category term="Librairie Avant-grade" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/tags/Librairie-Avant-grade/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Ode to State&#39;s Fallen Warriors 《楚辭•九歌·國殤》英譯</title>
    <link href="https://onsaddle.github.io/2019/05/29/Ode-state-warrior/"/>
    <id>https://onsaddle.github.io/2019/05/29/Ode-state-warrior/</id>
    <published>2019-05-29T08:06:24.000Z</published>
    <updated>2019-10-15T15:29:12.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<br><p><img src="https://i.loli.net/2019/09/10/5JoHPQzO8ENKitU.jpg" alt="IMG_20180103_001744.jpg"></p><br><p><strong>Ode to State’s Fallen Warriors</strong> <br></p><p><em>Nine Odes, Songs of Chu<br>Qu Yuan (340-278 BC)</em><br><br></p><p>Wielding dagger-axes from Wu place<br>Wearing armors made of rhino hide<br>Warriors drove the chariots across the enemy’s<br>Engaging them hand to hand</p><p>Banners blocking the sun<br>Enemy swarmed like clouds<br>Under pouring rain of arrows<br>Chu warriors rushed to confront their foes</p><p>Our formation was broken<br>Our line was penetrated<br>The left horse was killed<br>The right horse was wounded by blades</p><p>Wheels trapped among corpses<br>Horses dragged unmovable<br>Yet they raised high the jade drum sticks<br>And the sound of battle drum burst out loud</p><p>The heaven was darkened<br>The earth roaring in rampage<br>The last warriors fell to the ground<br>Men’s bodies littered the land after brutal fight</p><p>Leaving home, they had no intent to return<br>Marching forward, they rode towards certain death<br>Endless plain they marched across<br>The land so vast, the journey so long</p><p>Only the longest sword a true warrior carries<br>The strongest bow he draws<br>Even when his head and body lie in different places<br>His soul can not be bent</p><p>A candid, fearless and martial people we are<br>Strong to the end. Can be conquered by none<br>The body dies. The spirit never<br>Even taken by death, a brave soul would still be the captain of ghosts.</p><br><p><em>2019年端午前夕譯，2019年9月改定</em><br><br><br><br></p><blockquote><p>國殤  </p><br><p><em>《楚辭•九歌》</em><br><em>屈原</em></p><br><p>操吳戈兮被犀甲，車錯轂兮短兵接；</p><p>旌蔽日兮敵若雲，矢交墜兮士爭先；</p><p>淩余陣兮躐余行，左驂殪兮右刃傷；</p><p>霾兩輪兮縶四馬，援玉枹兮擊鳴鼓；</p><p>天時懟兮威靈怒，嚴殺盡兮棄原野；</p><p>出不入兮往不反，平原忽兮路超遠；</p><p>帶長劍兮挾秦弓，首身離兮心不懲；</p><p>誠既勇兮又以武，終剛強兮不可淩；</p><p>身既死兮神以靈，魂魄毅兮為鬼雄。 </p></blockquote><br><p><img src="https://i.loli.net/2019/10/09/GsOtdSgp5FkfmT4.jpg" alt="DSC_2217.jpg"> 軎 (wèi) Bronze chariot axle cap. Hubei Provincial Museum.</p><p><img src="https://i.loli.net/2019/10/09/ZcMXhNg5xKkHT2R.jpg" alt="DSC_2230.jpg"> Bronze arrow heads. Hubei Provincial Museum.</p><p><img src="https://i.loli.net/2019/10/09/YmIndyPNF7kLXE6.jpg" alt="DSC_2209.jpg"> Leather armour. Hubei Provincial Museum.</p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        &lt;br&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.loli.net/2019/09/10/5JoHPQzO8ENKitU.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_20180103_001744.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ode to State’s Fal
      
    
    </summary>
    
    
      <category term="Skiff" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/categories/Skiff/"/>
    
    
      <category term="poem" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/tags/poem/"/>
    
      <category term="translation" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/tags/translation/"/>
    
      <category term="Chu" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/tags/Chu/"/>
    
      <category term="Qu Yuan" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/tags/Qu-Yuan/"/>
    
      <category term="Chuci" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/tags/Chuci/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Climbing Dabie 大別攀峰</title>
    <link href="https://onsaddle.github.io/2019/05/07/May-Dabie/"/>
    <id>https://onsaddle.github.io/2019/05/07/May-Dabie/</id>
    <published>2019-05-07T08:06:24.000Z</published>
    <updated>2020-03-05T19:11:38.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://i.loli.net/2020/03/02/2jSo4Dw6epcLfVg.jpg" alt="DSCN5173.JPG"></p><p><img src="https://i.loli.net/2019/09/29/wPIK1Yy5rlF78AT.jpg" alt="DSCN5175.JPG"></p><p><img src="https://i.loli.net/2019/09/29/tJE8OZyGw6YbuPV.jpg" alt="DSCN5160.JPG">  <u>Visited by a bee during siesta</u></p><p><img src="https://i.loli.net/2019/09/29/nNSkWCvBJR3utPl.jpg" alt="DSC_0815.JPG"> <u>Dawn at camp</u></p><br><p>假期去了羅田大別山。帶帳篷爬了兩個HC級長坡，薄刀峰1060米，天堂寨1110米，下到英山的張咀水庫露營。</p><p>盧梭在《一個孤獨漫步者的遐想》裡解釋說：“幸福是一種過於恒定的狀態，而人則是一個變化無常的客體，因此兩者合不來。” 為什麼喜歡長跑和騎長途？大約是在持久的運動中，風景的變化與個體的無常互相抵消，反而顯得恒定而單調，因而幸福就有了可能。</p><p>露營之夜總是睡得很早很沉。半夜在三尺厚的蛙聲中醒來，睜開眼。</p><p>一萬顆閃亮的眼睛，穿越了宇宙和群山那融為一體的黑暗，無聲地注視著我。震撼得無法言語。它們有的也許已經熄滅了。我们所见的一切都不是此刻的当下，而是光子启程之前世界的样子。</p><p>在远方的星球上，此时此刻，可能也有个露营者，正端详着我们的过去。</p><br><p>This May Day holiday I went to the sections of Dabie Mountains 大别山 in Luotian 罗田. Carrying my tent I climbed up two HC-class long slopes, Thin-blade-Ridge 薄刀峰 1060 meters, Paradise-Fort 天堂寨 1110 meters, and then descended to the Zhangzui reservoir 张咀水库 in Yingshan 英山 for camping.</p><p>“Happiness is a lasting state which does not seem to be made for man in this world. Everything here on earth is in a continual flux which allows nothing to assume any constant form …… It is only when I am alone that I am my own master, at all other times I am the plaything of all who surround me.” explained Rousseau in his <em>Reveries of the Solitary Walker</em>. Around the time of the long-lasting movement, like cycling and distance running, the changes in landscape and the impermanence of myself cancel each other. The momentariness assumes a constant form at last. Thus, happiness becomes possible.</p><p>Camping night is the rare time when I sleep very early and very sound. Waking up in the middle of the night in a three-foot-thick, dense chorus of frogs, I opened my eyes.</p><p>Above me were ten thousand shining eyes. Through the universe and the darkness of the mountains, which now have became one, they silently watched me. Stunned beyond words. Some of them may have already gone out. Everything we see is not the present moment, but the way the world was before the photons set off.</p><p>On a distant planet, at this moment, there may also be a camper, looking at our past.</p><br><hr><p><img src="https://i.loli.net/2019/09/29/bs1j7BZwRdKc2U6.jpg" alt="DSC_0828.JPG"> <u>Tea garden in Yingshan</u></p><p><img src="https://i.loli.net/2019/09/29/ap9CGUJTIyONHQn.jpg" alt="DSCN5109.JPG"> <u>This white fisherman is a patient Egret,  <em>Egretta garzetta</em>  白鹭</u></p><p><img src="https://i.loli.net/2019/09/29/FGRNXDpzQSnClAj.jpg" alt="DSCN5180.JPG"> <u>Collared crow, <em>Corvus torquatus</em> 白颈鸦</u> </p><p>route:</p><p><img src="https://i.loli.net/2020/03/06/6lsVEHb8K1afeN9.jpg" alt="map.JPG"></p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.loli.net/2020/03/02/2jSo4Dw6epcLfVg.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;DSCN5173.JPG&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.loli.net/2019/09/29/wPIK1Yy5r
      
    
    </summary>
    
    
      <category term="Yangtze" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/categories/Yangtze/"/>
    
    
      <category term="cycling" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/tags/cycling/"/>
    
      <category term="mountain" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/tags/mountain/"/>
    
      <category term="Dabie" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/tags/Dabie/"/>
    
      <category term="Hubei" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/tags/Hubei/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>How to Cook Your Boy 一孩兩吃</title>
    <link href="https://onsaddle.github.io/2019/04/17/son-sacrifice/"/>
    <id>https://onsaddle.github.io/2019/04/17/son-sacrifice/</id>
    <published>2019-04-17T08:06:24.000Z</published>
    <updated>2019-10-08T05:35:04.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>復活節快到了，郵箱newsletter裡開始有Easter火腿菜譜。很誘人。</p><p>看著看著想起來亞伯拉罕差點把兒子烤了獻祭的故事。</p><p>亞伯拉罕是虔誠的信徒，上帝讓他百歲得子。可後來又想考驗他，指示亞伯拉罕把這孩子放到山頂祭壇上以火烤之獻祭。</p><p>亞伯拉罕架起柴堆正待手起刀落，上帝派天使阻止了他。倫勃朗還有N多大師傅都畫過這一幕。畫上天使還帶著一頭頂替孩子的羊，亞伯拉罕後來就宰羊獻祭。</p><p>亞伯拉罕被基督教、猶太教、伊斯蘭教共同奉為先知，古蘭經說易蔔拉欣願以子獻祭，安拉賜福讓他獲羊以作犧牲，便是宰牲節的來歷。</p><hr><p><img src="https://i.loli.net/2019/09/11/Wkmi3vIYsbjD7U6.jpg" alt="Abrahams-near-sacrifice-of-Isaac.jpg"><em>Image from page 127 of “Delightful stories; or, Home talks out of the Wonderful book.” (1888). Public domain.</em></p><p><img src="https://i.loli.net/2019/09/11/s15KHjSEvmylgoJ.jpg" alt="abraham_8327.jpg"><em>Ibrahim sacrificing Ismail, with Jibrael presenting him with a lamb as replacement, from Zubdat al-Tawarikh.</em></p><hr><p>除了BBQ，小孩兒還有另一種吃法。</p><p>齊桓公所寵愛的大師傅叫易牙。有天小白跟易牙開了個玩笑，說寡人吃遍了山珍海味，如今就差沒吃過人肉了。隔天易牙以金盅進肉湯一道，味鮮無比。小白一口一口喝的開心，便問此是何湯。</p><p>易牙坦白：是我家熊孩子，祝君王長命百歲。</p><p>天津人說話：介倒楣孩子……</p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        &lt;p&gt;復活節快到了，郵箱newsletter裡開始有Easter火腿菜譜。很誘人。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;看著看著想起來亞伯拉罕差點把兒子烤了獻祭的故事。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;亞伯拉罕是虔誠的信徒，上帝讓他百歲得子。可後來又想考驗他，指示亞伯拉罕把這孩子放到山頂祭壇上以火烤之獻祭。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;
      
    
    </summary>
    
    
      <category term="Skiff" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/categories/Skiff/"/>
    
    
      <category term="son" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/tags/son/"/>
    
      <category term="sacrifice" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/tags/sacrifice/"/>
    
      <category term="humanity" scheme="https://onsaddle.github.io/tags/humanity/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
</feed>
